<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Endings Principles for Digital Longevity</title>
        <author>
          <orgName>The Endings Project Team</orgName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Encoded by Ash Clark in preparation for a panel on the Endings Principles. No changes were 
          made to the text of the Principles. However, the TEI elements chosen to represent the HTML may 
          not be exactly as the Principles’ creators intended them. Ash Clark is responsible for the 
          added categorization of each principle.</p>
        <p>The TEI file and accompanying materials are available under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons BY Attribution 4.0 
          International License</ref>.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>Endings Principles for Digital Longevity</title>
          <edition>Version 2.2.1</edition>
          <date when="2023-03-03">2023-03-03</date>
          <author>
            <orgName>The Endings Project Team</orgName>
          </author>
          <ptr target="https://endings.uvic.ca/principles.html"/>
          <note>
            <p>Available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">
              Creative Commons BY Attribution 4.0 International License</ref>.</p>
          </note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy>
          <category xml:id="cat.archiving" n="Archiving">
            <catDesc>This principle anticipates long-term preservation of the projects’ components.</catDesc>
            
            <category xml:id="cat.lockss" n="Lots of Copies Keep Stuff Safe (LOCKSS)">
              <catDesc>This principle encourages copying resources such that some version of them might 
                survive.</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="cat.provenance" n="Provenance">
              <catDesc>This principle supports record-keeping of the history of the project.</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          
          <category xml:id="cat.maintainability" n="Maintainability">
            <catDesc>This principle encourages the upkeep of a project’s components, keeping them in 
              sync during the project’s lifecycle.</catDesc>
            
            <category xml:id="cat.open-source" n="Open source">
              <catDesc>This principle participates in open source ecosystems, built on well-documented, 
                thoroughly-tested, and widely-adopted technologies.</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          
          <category xml:id="cat.usability" n="Usability">
            <catDesc>This principle ensures consistent, reliable, legible use of the project’s 
              end-products.</catDesc>
            
            <category xml:id="cat.reuse" n="Reuse">
              <catDesc>This principle supports reuse of materials outside of the project’s original 
                context.</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="cat.transparency" n="Transparency">
              <catDesc>This principle encourages discovery of and engagement with materials.</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-10">Expanded the <gi>teiHeader</gi> to include more information about this 
          TEI file’s relationship to the Endings Principles.</change>
        <change when="2025-04-07">Encoded the Principles from the Endings Project website, and tagged 
          them to create my own taxonomy.</change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <head>Principles</head>
      <head type="sub">Endings Principles for Digital Longevity</head>
      <p>Version 2.2.1, 2023-03-03</p>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>We divide digital projects into five primary components:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ref target="#data">Data</ref></item>
        <item><ref target="#documentation">Documentation</ref></item>
        <item><ref target="#processing">Processing</ref></item>
        <item><ref target="#products">Products</ref></item>
        <item><ref target="#release-management">Release management</ref></item>
      </list>
      
      <div xml:id="data">
        <head n="1">Data</head>
        <p>Data is the expression of the source information, knowledge, and expertise of our researchers. 
          The following principles apply to data:</p>
        <list>
          <item n="1.1" ana="#cat.reuse #cat.transparency #cat.archiving #cat.open-source">
            Data is stored only in formats that conform to open standards and that are amenable to 
            processing (TEI XML, GML, ODF, TXT).</item>
          <item n="1.2" ana="#cat.lockss #cat.transparency #cat.provenance">
            Data is subject to version control (Subversion, Git).</item>
          <item n="1.3" ana="#cat.maintainability">
            Data is continually subject to validation and diagnostic analysis.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="documentation">
        <head n="2">Documentation</head>
        <list>
          <item n="2.1" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.maintainability #cat.transparency #cat.reuse">
            Data models, including field names, descriptions, and controlled values, should be clearly 
            documented in a static document that is maintained with the data and forms part of the 
            products.</item>
          <item n="2.2" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.reuse #cat.transparency #cat.open-source">
            All rights and intellectual property issues should be clearly documented. Where possible the 
            Data and Products should be released under open licenses (Creative Commons, GNU, BSD, MPL).</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="processing">
        <head n="3">Processing</head>
        <p>Processing code is written and maintained by the project technical staff, and is also subject 
          to version control. Processing code provides all the following functions:</p>
        <list>
          <item n="3.1" ana="#cat.maintainability #cat.usability">
            <term>Relentless validation</term>: all processing includes validation/linting of all inputs 
            and outputs and all validation errors should exit the process and prevent further execution 
            until the errors are resolved.</item>
          <item n="3.2" ana="#cat.maintainability">
            <term>Continuous integration</term>: any change to the source data requires an entire 
            rebuild of the site (triggered automatically where possible).</item>
          <item n="3.3" ana="#cat.maintainability">
            Code is contingent: while code is not expected to have significant longevity, wherever 
            possible, all code should follow Endings principles for data and products.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="products">
        <head n="4">Products</head>
        <p>Products are the project outputs intended for end-users, typically in the form of websites or 
          print documents. The following principles apply to products intended for the web:</p>
        <list>
          <item n="4.1" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.maintainability">
            No dependence on server-side software: build a static website with no databases, no PHP, no 
            Python.</item>
          <item n="4.2" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.maintainability">
            No boutique or fashionable technologies: use only standards with support across all 
            platforms, whose long-term viability is assured. Our choices are HTML5, JavaScript, and CSS.</item>
          <item n="4.3" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.maintainability #cat.usability">
            No dependence on external libraries or services: no JQuery, no AngularJS, no Bootstrap, no 
            Google Search.</item>
          <item n="4.4" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.usability">
            No query strings: every entity in the site has a unique page with a simple URL that will 
            function on any domain or IP address.</item>
          <item n="4.5" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.lockss #cat.reuse #cat.transparency">
            Inclusion of data: every site should include a documented copy of the source data, so that 
            users of the site can repurpose the work easily.</item>
          <item n="4.6" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.lockss">
            Massive redundancy: every page contains all the components it needs, so that it will 
            function without the rest of the site if necessary, even though doing so means duplicating 
            information across the site.</item>
          <item n="4.7" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.usability">
            Graceful failure: every page should still function effectively even in the absence of 
            JavaScript or CSS support.</item>
        </list>
        <p>These principles are tempered by the following concessions:</p>
        <list>
          <item n="4.8" ana="#cat.usability">
            Once a fully-working static site is achieved, it may be enhanced by the use of other 
            services such as a server-side indexing tool (Solr, eXist) to support searching and similar 
            functionality.</item>
          <item n="4.9" ana="#cat.usability">
            The use of an external library may be necessary to support a specific function that is too 
            complex to be coded locally (such as mapping or cryptography). Any such libraries must be 
            open-source and widely-used, and must not themselves have dependencies.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="release-management">
        <head n="5">Release management</head>
        <p>Release management handles the public release of products. These principles apply to release 
          management:</p>
        <list>
          <item n="5.1" ana="#cat.maintainability #cat.provenance">
            Releases should be periodical and carefully planned. The “rolling release” model should be 
            avoided.</item>
          <item n="5.2" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.maintainability">
            A release should only be made when the entire product set is coherent, consistent, and 
            complete (passing all validation and diagnostic tests).</item>
          <item n="5.3" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.maintainability #cat.provenance">
            Like editions of print works, each release of a web resource should be clearly identified on 
            every page by its build date and some kind of version number.</item>
          <item n="5.4" ana="#cat.provenance #cat.usability #cat.transparency">
            Web resources should include detailed instructions for citation, so that end-users can 
            unambiguously cite a specific page from a specific edition.</item>
          <item n="5.5" ana="#cat.archiving #cat.transparency #cat.usability">
            URLs for individual resources within a digital publication should persist across editions. 
            Any moved, retired, or deleted resources no longer available at a previously accessible URL 
            should be redirected appropriately.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
